Rajesh kumar

Sr. SCM Engineer / Build & Release Engineer

Email : rajeshkumar.raj06@gmail.com

Mobile : +91-8105843520 DOB - 04 Sept 1984

Career Summary

Total, Over 7 years of extensive experience in SCM domain having depth knowledge of Configuration Management, Build and Installer, Release Management and Application Management. Expertise in Wide range of CM tools (Perforce, Git, SVN and MKS), packaging tools (Wise Studio/InstallAnywhere) and Build Management (Ant, Jenkins, CruiseControl, Anthillpro, Maven, BuildForge & Bambo) and scripting such as Perl with multisite projects. Ability to cope up with any complex situation and innovation

Objectives

To work in an environment of inspiring and self-motivational team of professionals, where I can make significant contribution to an organization while enhancing my skills further.

Experience Summary

- ✓ Sr. SCM Engineer at <u>Adobe Systems</u> (April 2011 to Continue...)
- ✓ Sr. Build & Release Engineer at Emptoris (IBM) Technologies (May 2010 to April 2011)
- ✓ Sr. Build & Release at Ness Technologies (September 2009 to May 2010)
- ✓ Sr. Engineer at MindTree Ltd. (August 2006 to September 2009)
- √ Jr. Software Engineer at Accenture India (September 2005 July 2006)

Education Summary

- ✓ Master in Science (Information Technology), Annamalai University, 2006 2009
- ✓ Bachelor of Information Technology, JSSATE, Bangalore 2001-2004
- ✓ Higher National Diploma in Computing & Multimedia, Edexcel Foundation, UK

Skills Set

	Area of Expertise
Languages	Perl, HTML, Core Java, PHP
CM Tools	Perforce, Git, MKS Integrity, CVS, VSS
CI Tools	Jenkins , BuildForge, AnthillPro, Bamboo, Cruise Control
Packaging Tools	Wise Installer/ Studio, InstallAnywhere, Linux RPM
OS	Windows 2000/NT/98/95/XP, Redhat Linux, Solaris, Ubuntu
Scripting	Perl, Ant, Shell Scripting, Maven, Gmake, JavaScript
App Servers	Apache HTTP, Apache Tomcat, WAMP, XAMP, Jboss
Design	Adobe PhotoShop CS 6, Flash CS, CSS, Visio(Tool), DreamWeaver CS
Databases	MySQL 5, Oracle 9i
Coverage - Analysis	Emma, Sonar, PMD, Checkstyle
CMS/other Tools	Joomla, Drupal, WordPress, PhpBB, Elgg, BugZilla, JIRA, Gforge, Wiki
Virtualization	VMware, Echos

Awards and Recognitions

- ✓ **Team of the Year 2006-07** A part of the Team of the year 2006-07 of MindTree Ltd.
- ✓ <u>Spot Award 2007</u> For Excellent work in Install and Packaging for the Link Manager Product in short span of time using Wise Package Studio.
- ✓ <u>Team Spot Award 2007</u> To Setup and Configure the Complex Build and CM system in LSD consisting of 150+ project without having support from outgoing onsite team.
- ✓ <u>Team Spot Award 2008</u> To Contribute in Styx Development and setup Wise Packaging system and delivered on time which was highly appreciated by clients.
- ✓ <u>Shining Star Awards 2008</u>- To make the most successful Release ever happened in Symantec LSD team.
- ✓ <u>Osmosis 2008 Techworks Contest winner</u> To develop a Build system, Antares, A Build Management System.
- ✓ <u>Outstanding KM Leads Awards 2009</u> To setup knowledge Management Process/Practice across 240 MindTree Project.
- ✓ **Author, Editor and Moderators** of ScmGalaxy.com
- ✓ **Successfully transition SCM** (CM, Build and Release) Training for Client's team in London, UK in 2009.

Roles & Responsibilities in details

- ✓ Maintain, manage, enhance and own builds and releases to various environments, such as development, QA, pre-production and production.
- ✓ Manage source code version control system and Build server
- ✓ Develop and maintain an efficient and flexible automated deployment framework that ensures repeatable and reliable deployment of releases into multiple environments
- ✓ Provide deployment and troubleshooting support.
- ✓ Implement branching and merging strategies for major, minor, maintenance and patch releases.
- ✓ Author internal documentation, such as build procedures; build release notes, and installation/configuration notes.
- ✓ Coordinate builds of a release with QA and Release Team.
- ✓ Provide quick resolution to build issues.
- ✓ 7+ years' of experience as a build/release/deployment management engineer.
- ✓ Proven track record of success and excellence in working on enterprise class large scale applications in production environments.
- ✓ Expert in Source Code Management Tools such as Perforce, Git, CSV, MKS, VSS and SVN.
- ✓ Expert in web-based build and deployment tools such as BuildForge, AnthillPro, CruiseControl, Bamboo
- ✓ Strong working knowledge of Perl or shell scripts, Batch, Ant
- ✓ Detailed knowledge of the Unix/Linux operation system and tools.
- ✓ Sound understanding of web technologies and VMware.
- ✓ Excellent problem solving, analytical skills and technical troubleshooting skills

I. Adobe Systems – Perforce and BuildForge Administrator

Project Description: Working as a Senior SCM Engineer in a team of 4 members, responsible for handling 15 Perforce servers which has more than 150 perforce instance, 150+ proxy and 5000+ users and 10 Terabytes disk space. I am also responsible to handle 30+ Continuous integration build forge servers. Currently we are handling 35+ RedHat Linux Machine for our application hosting purpose. Development teams are located in Seattle, Minnesota, Canada, Ireland, England, Germany, Japan, and India.

Environment/Skills: Perforce, Redhat Linux, Shell Scripting, Perl, Jenkins and BuildForge **Role and responsibilities:**

Perforce Server Administration task includes....

- √ Application administration for all Perforce servers
- ✓ Manage user accounts, groups, licenses and security on all Perforce servers.
- ✓ Perforce server / proxy / remote depots Setup, Upgrade, Migration and maintenance.
- ✓ Monitoring of all perforce servers up and down events and take appropriate measures to make up all the time.
- ✓ Performance monitoring which including monitoring suspicious user's activities which might block others users activities on the same server.
- ✓ Maintain the standard and processed adhered by all the team's
- ✓ Monitoring the Large process which has ability to consume more RAM, detect and kill it using automation script / manually.
- ✓ Create & test scripts needed for effective & efficient use of Perforce.
- ✓ Monitoring Disk Space and cleanup activities and prepare maintenance, backup/archival and DR plans
- ✓ Design and implement utilities to set up and monitor the various development tools, CM and integration testing environments
- ✓ Address Perforce Education and Training needs by identifying the kind of training, tools, depot structure, branching, group policies, security and scripting and user documentation required.

BuildForge Server Administration task includes....

- ✓ Setting up the new server / Upgrades and Maintenance
- ✓ Project Data backup and Restore.
- √Troubleshooting and Debugging of the issues in BuildForge
- ✓ Training and Documentation

I. Emptoris Technologies – Services Procurement - A Java Based Project

Project Description: Emptoris Services Procurement delivers transparency into an organization's services spend, demand and procurement process. It automates the entire complex purchasing workflow for multiple categories, including IT outsourcing, contingent

labor, facilities management, business consulting and marketing, and enforces compliance with laws, policies and controls

Environment/Skills: Perforce, Ant, Redhat Linux, Shell Scripting, Jira, Emma, Sonar, Hudson **Role and responsibilities:**

- ✓ Supporting team for Build & Release requirement & Responsible for daily build and Request Build
- ✓ Plan configuration and New Project Setup in Hudson
- ✓ Ant script changes according to branch/release specification
- ✓ Build debugging in case of build failure.
- ✓ Helping team in Release Activity (Code Completion, Code Freeze, Branching, Tagging and Release of Build)
- ✓ Build Server and CM server management, plugins integration, upgrade and maintenance.
- ✓ Build Automation and Build deployment and Smoke Testing
- ✓ EMMA & Sonar Implementation
- ✓ Linux System Administration

I. Ness Technologies - Chordiant CFS - A Java Based Project

Project Description: Chordaint Foundation Server is a set of distributed component that work together to provide an execution environment for eBusiness applications. Using Chordiant Forundation Server, you can create distributed multi-channel, multi-datastore and data driven eBusiness applications based on open standards that can be adapted for future technologies. **Environment/Skills:** Subversion, Bamboo, Maven, Ant, Solaris, Shell Scripting, Jira, FishEye, Crucible, Clover, Crowd, Sonar

Role and responsibilities:

- ✓ Supporting team for Build & Release requirement & Responsible for daily build
- ✓ Plan configuration and New Project Setup in Bamboo and Debugging
- ✓ Maven script changes according to branch/release specification
- ✓ Helping team in Release Activity (Code Completion, Code Freeze, Branching, Tagging and Release of Build)
- ✓ Build Server and CM server management, plugins integration, upgrade and maintenance.

III. MindTree Ltd. - Symantec LiveState Delivery - A Java and C++ Based Project

Project Description: LiveState Delivery provides the capabilities that administrator can successfully automate client management tasks, such as provisioning, configuring, updating, and migrating computers. You can encapsulate management tasks into packages that are sent to computers with Windows, UNIX, Linux, Pocket PC operating systems. LiveState Delivery lets you manage computers and mobile devices throughout their lifecycle by leveraging proven technologies, including agent-based deployment, imaging, and native installation.

Environment/Skills: MKS Integrity, Perforce, Ant, Suse Linux, AnthillPro, Gforge, InstallAnywhere and Tomcat, Shell Scripting, Batch Scripting

Role and responsibilities:

The primary responsibilities include:

- ✓ MKS Integrity Administrator in Suse Linux Environment & Perforce administration in Win2003
- ✓ Configuration Manager in Perforce multisite environment
- ✓ Acted as a Release Manager and Install engineer additional
- √ Automating builds using Ant scripting/batch programming in Anthillpro
- ✓ Responsible for Daily builds, Continuous build and patch builds
- ✓ Setup of Build Machine, Software configuration, Cleaning and maintaining the Build machines.
- ✓ User Management and administration in CM and Build tools
- ✓ Setting up Build environment in Windows and Linux Environment
- Communicating the build breaks to the developers on time and providing workarounds in order to move on the build cycle time frame.

IV. MindTree Ltd. - Symantec Ghost Solution Suite - A .Net Based Project

Project Description: A Remote Access Management Project, Symantec Ghost Solution Suite is the industry's most widely used enterprise imaging and deployment solution with ease-of-use for managing the entire PC lifecycle, including OS deployment with hardware-independent imaging, software distribution, easy migration of user settings and profiles, and secure PC retirement.

Environment/Skills: Perforce, Wise Studio, Continuum and Gforge **Role and responsibilities:**

- ✓ Acting a CM and Build Server administrator for Perforce and Continuum build server
- ✓ Automating builds using Ant scripting and Continuum
- ✓ Creating Installer using Wise installer for Hot Fix, Patch and Services pack Release

V. MindTree Ltd. - Symantec GoEveryWhere - A PHP and JS based Project

Project Description: GoEverywhere is a secure online workspace or storage hub which allows users to access and use web applications regardless of where users are or which computer they are using. Users can access web applications to do word processing, carry out spreadsheet work, prepare presentation slides, read Gmail, etc. All the web applications will be aggregated into a single palette, known as webtop screen by Symantec.

Environment/Skills: Subversion, RPM, Ant, RedHat Linux and CruiseControl **Role and responsibilities:**

- ✓ Creation of RPM Packages and RMP packaging for Redhat Linux based distribution system
- ✓ Build Automation and RPM package Deployment Automation
- ✓ CM and Build Server setup and Maintenance.

✓ Multimedia and design layout support using Photoshop and HTML

VI. MindTree Ltd - LiveState Package Manager – A C++ and .Net Based Project

Project Description: The LiveState Delivery Package Manager provides everything that user need to create, modify and manage your Symantec LiveState packages. User can connect to a LiveState Configuration Server to download packages to modify, and publish new packages. User can create new packages by manually specifying all the necessary information, or user can use the packaging tools to create new packages, and then open them in the Package Manager to make necessary modifications before publishing them

Environment/Skills: Perforce, Visual Studio 2003, Ant, AnthillPro and Gforge Role and responsibilities:

- ✓ Setup and configuration of CM server and build server
- ✓ Establish the CM, build and Release Process across the team.
- ✓ Involvement in Branching, Labeling, tagging and Release activities.

VII. MindTree Ltd - Link Manager - A Java Based Project

Project Description: A Web based tool develop in Java

Environment/Skills: Application Packaging, Wise Studio, Wise Scripting, VB Scripting, Tomcat and

Jboss

Role and responsibilities:

- ✓ Creating an Installer using Wise Studio for Hotfix, Patch Release and Major release
- ✓ Creating windows installer packages for W2K, XP & Vista

VIII. Accenture India Ltd - BellSouth, US

Project Description: Bellsouth recognized as one of the leading worldwide providers of IP-based communications services to businesses. We also have the nation's fastest 3G network and the largest international coverage of any U.S. wireless carrier, offering the most phones that work in the most countries; the largest Wi-Fi network in the United States; and the largest number of high speed Internet access subscribers in the United States.

Environment/Skills: Harvest, Unix, Shell Scripting, Oracle 9i, Defect & Feature Management, Role and responsibilities:

Worked as Configuration and package Engineer in Unix Environment. Worked in Project and Configuration Management. Set up Defects and Features for DDS, create packages and Install into Servers, wrote PL/SQL and Shell scripting to run on the server and Configure Software lifecycle management for Different Releases Using Internal tools.